<document title="MoRE - the emulator" author="Patrick" area="tools" keyword="">
<section id="moreintro" title="Introduction">
<![CDATA[
The MoRE (MoSync Runtime Environment) emulator provides a reference implementation
of MoSync for the PC. It acts as a virtual machine directly executing MoSync bytecode. 
However, it's not only a compilant MoSync implementation - it's the actual reference 
implementation that all the real device platforms are required to conform to!
\\
\\
MoRE can be controlled either by pressing the keys on the graphical phone, or using a
number of keyboard shortcuts:
\\
{{images/MoRE_diagram.png}}

MoRE doesn't emulate any phone in particular, but its behavior when exeuting MoSync
application reflects that of the target device. For instance, the screen dimensions vary
according to those of the target device.

MoRE communicates with the MoSync IDE, sending call stacks, panics, and other useful
data to be presented in the console window.

MoRE can be controlled either by pressing the graphical buttons and keys, or by using
PC keyboard shortcuts:
]]>
</section>

<section id="profiles" title="Using profiles">
<![CDATA[
When a target device is selected in the IDE, MoRE is configured to reflect the properties
of that device. Currently, the only supported property is the screen size. You can manually
override the screen size setting by clicking the arrow next to the "play" button in the toolbar,
and selecting "Run Configurations":

{{images/MoRE_screensize.png}}
]]>
</section>

<section id="debugging" title="Debugging">
<![CDATA[
When a MoSync application terminates because of a panic, a call stack is transmitted to the
output console in the IDE:
\\
{{images/MoRE_callstack.png}}
\\
The call stack shows you all the stack frames that were active when the application terminated,
and you can click on each line to go to the corresponding source file and line. This is the format of such lines:

[code filename="dummy.h"]
IP:<instruction pointer>: <path to source file>:<line number in source file>
[/code]



If the panic involved MoSync libraries that you do not have the source code to, those lines will not be clickable.
]]>
</section>


</document>
